<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
    which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC0791 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0791.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2113 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2113.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2357 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2357.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2460 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2711 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2711.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2784 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2784.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2827 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2827.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2914 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2914.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3048 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3048.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3269 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3269.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3550 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3630 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3630.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3738 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3738.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4302 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4302.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4609 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4609.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4727 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4727.xml"> <!-- TBD: remove when/if non-experimental -->
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6398 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6398.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6807 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6807.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7450 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7450.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7761 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7761.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker.xml">
<!ENTITY IEEE.754.1985 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml2/reference.IEEE.754.1985.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
    please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
    (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
    (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-jholland-cb-assisted-cc-00" ipr="trust200902">
 <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
    ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
       or pre5378Trust200902
    you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN" 
    they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

 <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
   <title abbrev="CBACC: Protocol Specification">Circuit Breaker Assisted Congestion Control (CBACC): Protocol Specification</title>

   <author fullname="Jacob Holland" initials="J.H." 
           surname="Holland">
     <organization>Akamai Technologies, Inc.</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>150 Broadway</street>
         <city>Cambridge</city>
         <region>Massachusetts</region>
         <code>02142</code>
         <country>USA</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+1 617 444 3000</phone>
       <email>jholland@akamai.com</email>
       <uri>https://www.akamai.com/</uri>
     </address>
   </author>
   <date year="2016" />
   <area>Transport</area>
   <workgroup>Transport Area Working Group</workgroup>

   <keyword>congestion control</keyword>
   <keyword>circuit breaker</keyword>
   <keyword>network transport circuit breaker</keyword>
   <keyword>multicast</keyword>
   <keyword>UDP</keyword>

   <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

   <abstract>
       <t>
           This document specifies Circuit Breaker Assisted Congestion Control (CBACC),
           which provides bandwidth information from senders to intermediate network
           nodes to enable good decisions for fast-trip Network Transport Circuit Breaker
           activity (<xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker" />) when
           necessary for network health. CBACC is specifically designed to support
           protocols using IP multicast, particularly as a supplement to receiver-driven
           congestion control protocols such as WEBRC <xref target="RFC3738" />,
           to help affected networks rapidly detect and mitigate the impact of scenarios in
           which a network is oversubscribed to flows which are not responsive to congestion.
       </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
   <section title="Introduction">
       <t>
           This document specifies Circuit Breaker Assisted Congestion Control (CBACC).
       </t>
       <t>
           CBACC is a congestion control building block designed for use with IP traffic
           that has a known maximum bandwidth, which does not reduce its sending rate in response
           to congestion. CBACC is specifically designed to supplement protocols using
           WEBRC <xref target="RFC3738" /> or other receiver-driven multicast congestion
           control systems that rely on well-behaved receivers to achieve congestion
           control in a very highly scalable system (up to millions of receivers) without a
           feedback path that reduces sending rates by senders.
       </t>
       <t>
           CBACC addresses a vulnerability to "overjoining", a condition in which receivers
           (particularly malicious receivers) subscribe to traffic which, from the sending side,
           is non-responsive to congestion.
           Overjoining attacks and the challenges they present are discussed in more detail in
           Appendix A.
       </t>
       <t>
           A careful reading of the congestion control requirements of UDP Best Practices
           <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis" /> suggests that a network that forwards
           multicast traffic is required to operate a circuit breaker to maintain network
           health under a persistent overjoining condition, at a cost of cutting off some
           or all multicast traffic across the network during high congestion.
       </t>
       <t>
           CBACC provides a mechanism for networks to mitigate the impact of network overjoining by
           sender advertising of bandwidth information sufficient to implement a fast-trip circuit
           breaker <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker" />
           within a single network node which can specifically block the most problematic
           flows, and which can ensure the remaining flows fit within desired network
           parameters.
       </t>
       <t>
           In conjunction with receiver counts (e.g. via <xref target="RFC6807" />)
           such nodes can also provide much improved network fairness for circuit breaking
           decisions during an overjoining condition.
       </t>
       <t>
           In addition to streams using WEBRC, CBACC may also be suitable for use with other
           traffic, both unicast and multicast, that does not respond to congestion by reducing
           sending rates, including certain profiles of RTP <xref target="RFC3550" />
           over either unicast or multicast, as well as several tunneling protocols (e.g. AMT
           <xref target="RFC7450" /> and GRE <xref target="RFC2784" />) when they are known to carry
           traffic that would be suitable for CBACC. A complete specification for use of CBACC
           with unicast protocols and with tunneling protocols is out of scope for this document,
           though the security issues section does mention a few special considerations for potential
           unicast usage.
       </t>
       <t>
           CBACC-compliant senders transmit Bandwidth Advertisements through the same transport path as
           the data traffic, so that circuit breakers can make informed decisions about how flows
           should be prioritized for circuit breaking. Additionally, CBACC-compliant circuit breakers
           transmit information to receivers about flows which have been or might soon be circuit-broken,
           to encourage CBACC-aware applications to use alternate methods to retrieve
           equivalent (though probably lower-quality and possibly less efficient) data when possible.
       </t>
       <t>
           This document describes a building block as defined in <xref target="RFC3048" />.
           This document describes a congestion control building block that conforms to
           <xref target="RFC2357" />. This document follows the general guidelines provided in
           <xref target="RFC3269" />, in addition to the requirements on RFCs from
           <xref target="RFC5226" /> and <xref target="RFC3552" />.
       </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Terminology">
       <texttable anchor="definitions">
           <ttcol align="center">Term</ttcol>
           <ttcol align="center">Definition</ttcol>
           <c>circuit breaker</c><c>See <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker" /></c>
           <c>controlled environment</c><c>See <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis" /> Section 3.6</c>
           <c>general internet</c><c>See <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis" /> Section 3.6</c>
           <c>flow</c><c>traffic for a single (source,destination) IP pair, including destinations that are group addresses</c>
           <c>upstream</c><c>along a network topology path in the direction of a flow's sender</c>
           <c>downstream</c><c>along a network topology path in the direction of a flow's receiver</c>
           <c>ingress interface</c><c>the (single) upstream interface for a flow in a circuit breaker</c>
           <c>egress interface</c><c>a downstream interface for a flow in a circuit breaker</c>
       </texttable>
       <t>
           The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
           "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to
           be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119" />.
       </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Rationale">
       <!-- Required by https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.1.8
            Provide justification for the building block's existence
            Provide rationale for the building block's granularity
       -->
       <t>
           CBACC is defined as an independent congestion control building block instead
           of as an extension to WEBRC because it would be an equally useful supplement
           for other kinds of experimental receiver-driven multicast congestion control schemes,
           such as <xref target="PLM" /> or other methods based on receiver-driven conformance
           to a measurement of available network bandwidth or congestion.
       </t>
       <t>
           CBACC is also potentially valuable, even without other congestion control systems, in
           controlled environments where congestion control may not be required (e.g. for
           certain profiles of RTP <xref target="RFC3550" />), since CBACC can provide protection
           for such a network against congestion due to sender or network mis-configuration.
       </t>
       <t>
           CBACC provides a new form of communication between senders and network transit
           nodes to facilitate fast-trip circuit breakers as described in section 5.1 of
           <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker" /> which are not available
           via previously existing methods. When used in conjunction with compatible circuit breakers,
           CBACC can greatly improve the safety of a network that accepts and delivers interdomain
           massively scalable multicast traffic to potentially untrusted receivers.
       </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Applicability">
       <!-- Required by https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.1.8
            Intended usage
            Failure modes (including means of detection if known)
            Environmental considerations
            Incompatibilities / Conflicts with other building blocks
       -->
       <t>
           CBACC relies on the presence of CBACC-aware circuit breakers on a flow's
           transit path in order to provide congestion control in a network. In the absence
           of any CBACC-aware circuit breakers on a network path, CBACC constitutes a small
           extra overhead to a flow that provides no additional value.
       </t>
       <t>
           CBACC provides a form of congestion control for massively scalable protocols
           using the IP multicast service. CBACC is best used in conjunction with another
           receiver-driven multicast congestion control, but it is also suitable for
           use even without another congestion control mechanism, or when presence of another
           congestion control mechanism is unproven, such as when accepting multicast joins from
           untrusted receivers.
       </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Protocol Specification">
       <section title="Overview">
           <t>
               CBACC senders send Bandwidth Advertisement packets to advertise the maximum
               sending bandwidth along the data path for a flow through a network.
           </t>
           <t>
               CBACC bandwidth information is monitored by CBACC circuit breakers along the network
               path, which may block the forwarding of traffic for some flows in order to maintain
               network health. When a flow is blocked, a CBACC circuit breaker sets a bit in 
               Bandwidth Advertisement packets before they're forwarded downstream that indicates
               to subscribed receivers of that flow that traffic has been blocked.
           </t>
           <t>
               An effort is also made to notify downstream receivers when a flow is in danger of
               being circuit broken in the near future. This gives applications an opportunity
               to gracefully shift to a lower-bandwidth version of the same content, when possible,
               providing an early warning system against potential congestion.
           </t>
           <t>
               A Bandwidth Advertisement packet constitutes an "ingress meter"
               as described in section 3.1 of <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker" />.
               The configured bandwidth caps of egress interfaces likewise constitute "egress
               meters". However, the diagram in the referenced document is simplified by running
               the ingress and egress on the same network node. At the CBACC-aware circuit
               breaker, that node has both pieces of information as soon as a Bandwidth
               Advertisement is received, and can trip the circuit breaker if the aggregate
               CBACC bandwidth exceeds the bandwidth available on any egress interfaces.
           </t>
       </section>

       <section title="Packet Header Fields">
           <!-- Required by https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.1.8
                Specification of logical packet-header fields
                Abstract messages specifications
           -->
           <section title="Introduction">
               <t>
                   The initial draft of this document proposes 2 different methods of encapsulating
                   the Bandwidth Advertisement with a discussion of the known pros and cons of each. The
                   intent is to solicit feedback from the community and then settle on one
                   encapsulation (possibly a different, as yet unconsidered one).
               </t>
           </section>

           <section anchor="BandwidthAdv" title="Bandwidth Advertisement">
               <section title="As an IP header option">
                   <t>
                       Bandwidth advertisement can appear as either an IPv4 header option (as in
                       Section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC0791" />) or as an IPv6 extension header
                       option (as in section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC2460" />). They have the same
                       layout:
                   </t>
                   <figure align="center" anchor="option_layout">
                       <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|     Type      |     Length    |B|D|         Reserved          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                           Bandwidth                           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
                   </figure>
                   <t>
                       Bandwidth advertisements sent as IPv4 header options use option value [TBD],
                       with the "copied" bit set and the option class "control", as specified in
                       <xref target="RFC0791" /> section 3.1. Until and unless IANA
                       assigns a value, this will be option number 158 as described in section 8 of
                       <xref target="RFC4727" /> for experiments using IPv4 Option types. 
                       The length field is 8.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                       Bandwidth advertisements sent as IPv6 header options use option value [TBD],
                       with the "action" bits set to "skip" and the "change" bit set to 1, as specified in
                       <xref target="RFC2460" /> section 4.2. Until and unless IANA
                       assigns a value, this will be option number 0x3e as described in section 8 of
                       <xref target="RFC4727" /> for experiments using IPv6 Option Types.
                       The length field is 6.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                       Using an IP header option has the benefit of exposing the bandwidth to
                       all CBACC-compatible routers, in much the same way the IP Router Alert
                       option would, but without being processed or causing undue load in non-CBACC
                       routers.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                       The IP Header encapsulations DO work with IPSEC. As described in Appendix A of
                       <xref target="RFC4302" />, the IP header fields are properly treated as mutable and
                       zeroed for the IPSEC ICV calculations. CBACC circuit breakers MAY change bits in
                       transit. The Bandwidth Advertisement header itself IS NOT protected by IPSEC security
                       services, but protection of other parts of the packet remain unchanged.
                   </t>
               </section>
               <section title="As a UDP packet">
                   <t>
                       Bandwidth advertisements can appear as a UDP packet with destination port [TBD].
                       Until and unless IANA assigns a value, this will be port number 1022, one of the
                       experimental ports provided in Section 6 of <xref target="RFC4727" />. The UDP
                       packet contains a payload with the following packet format:
                   </t>
                   <figure align="center" anchor="udp_layout">
                       <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 0                   1
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|B|D|         Reserved          |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                               |
+      Bandwidth (32 bits)      +
|                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
                   </figure>
                   <t>
                       Using a dedicated UDP packet has the benefit of following the guidelines from
                       section 2.2.5 of <xref target="RFC3269" />, that Reliable Multicast Building Blocks MUST
                       initially define packet formats for use over UDP until such time as the protocol
                       is sufficiently widely deployed and understood. However, since the Bandwidth
                       Advertisement packets will be processed by intermediate network nodes while being
                       transmitted along the same routing path as the corresponding data packets, it
                       will be necessary to add an IP Router Alert option (<xref target="RFC2113" />
                       and <xref target="RFC2711" />) to the appropriate packets to flag them for the
                       circuit-breaker's examination. It's important to note that
                       <xref target="RFC6398" /> specifically
                       recommends against using the Router Alert option in the end-to-end open
                       Internet, which may impede experimentation and would very likely impede early
                       adoption.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                       An additional disadvantage of UDP relative to the IP header option is
                       that CBACC in UDP cannot be used for unicast tunnels, because the UDP port is the
                       only discriminator for the Bandwidth Advertisement.
                   </t>
                   <t>
                       <!-- "support for IPSEC MUST be explicitly shown", from
                            https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.2.5 -->
                       The UDP encapsulation DOES NOT work with IPSEC, because middle boxes can't
                       unpack or modify the Bandwidth Advertisement packets. [TO BE REMOVED: Does this violate
                       <xref target="RFC3269" /> section 2.2.5?]
                   </t>
               </section>
               <section title="Field definitions">
                   <section title="Bandwidth">
                       <t>
                           As in several other protocols sending bandwidth values such as OSPF-TE
                           <xref target="RFC3630" />, the bandwidth is expressed in bytes per second (not bits),
                           in IEEE floating point format. For quick reference, this format is as follows:
                       </t>
                       <figure align="center" anchor="ieee_float_layout">
                           <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|S|    Exponent   |                  Fraction                   |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
]]></artwork>
                       </figure>
                       <t>
                           S is the sign, Exponent is the exponent base 2 in "excess 127"
                           notation, and Fraction is the mantissa - 1, with an implied binary
                           point in front of it.  Thus, the above represents the value:
                       </t>
                       <figure align="center" anchor="ieee_float_equation">
                           <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
(-1)**(S) * 2**(Exponent-127) * (1 + Fraction)
]]></artwork>
                           <postamble>For more details, refer to <xref target="IEEE.754.1985" />.</postamble>
                       </figure>
                   </section>
                   <section title="B (Blocked) bit">
                       <t>
                           Indicates that the flow has been circuit-broken.
                       </t>
                   </section>
                   <section title="D (Danger) bit">
                       <t>
                           Indicates that the flow is in danger of being circuit-broken.
                       </t>
                   </section>
                   <section title="Reserved bits">
                       <t>
                           The sender MUST set all reserved bits to 0 when sending a CBACC control packet.
                           Receivers MUST accept any value in the reserved bits.
                       </t>
                   </section>
               </section>
           </section>
       </section>

       <section title="States">
           <section title="Interface State">
               <t>
                   A CBACC circuit breaker holds the following state for each interface, for both
                   the inbound and outbound directions on that interface:
                   <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
                       <t hangText="aggregate bandwidth">
                           The sum of the bandwidths of all non-circuit-broken CBACC flows which
                           transit this interface in this direction.
                       </t>
                       <t hangText="bandwidth limit">
                           The maximum aggregate CBACC bandwidth allowed, not including
                           circuit-broken flows. This may depend on administrative configuration
                           and congestion measurements for the network, whether from this node
                           or other nodes.
                           It's out of scope for this document to define such congestion
                           measurements. Network operators should carefully consider that this
                           bandwidth limit applies to flows that are unresponsive to congestion.
                           <vspace blankLines="1" />
                           When reducing the bandwidth limit due to congestion,
                           the circuit breaker MUST NOT reduce the limit by more than half its value in
                           10 seconds, and SHOULD use a smoothing function to reduce the limit gradually
                           over time.
                           <vspace blankLines="1" />
                           It is RECOMMENDED that no more than half the capacity for a
                           link be allocated to CBACC flows if the link might be shared with TCP or
                           other traffic that is responsive to congestion.
                           <vspace blankLines="1" />
                           Depending on administrative configuration and the physical characteristics
                           of the interface, the bandwidth limit may be either shared between
                           upstream and downstream traffic, or it may be separate. Either a single
                           shared value should be used, or two separate independent values should
                           be used for the inbound and outbound directions for an interface.
                       </t>
                       <t hangText="CBACC bandwidth warning threshold">
                           A soft bandwidth threshold. When the aggregate CBACC bandwidth exceeds
                           this threshold, flows that would have been circuit-broken with a bandwidth
                           limit at this threshold MUST have the Danger bit set in the Bandwidth
                           Advertisement packets that are forwarded by this circuit breaker.
                           This threshold SHOULD be configurable as a proportion of the bandwidth limit,
                           and MUST remain at or below the bandwidth limit when the bandwidth limit
                           changes. The recommended proportion value is .75, but specific networks may
                           use a different value if deemed useful by the network operators.
                       </t>
                   </list>
               </t>
           </section>
           <section title="Flow State">
               <t>
                   The following state is kept for flows that are joined from at least one
                   downstream interface and for which at least one CBACC Bandwidth Advertisement
                   packet has been received:
                   <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
                       <t hangText="bandwidth">
                           The bandwidth from the most receintly received Bandwidth Advertisement.
                       </t>
                       <t hangText="ingress status">
                           One of the following values:<list style="empty">
                               <t>* 'subscribed'<vspace blankLines="0" />
                                   Indicates that the circuit breaker is subscribed upstream to the
                                   flow and forwarding data and control packets through zero or more
                                   egress interfaces.
                               </t>
                               <t>* 'pruned'<vspace blankLines="0" />
                                   Indicates that the flow has been circuit-broken. A request to unsubscribe
                                   from the flow has been sent upstream, e.g. a PIM prune (section 3.5 of
                                   <xref target="RFC7761" />) or a "leave" operation via IGMP, MLD, or another
                                   appropriate group membership protocol.
                               </t>
                               <t>* 'probing'<vspace blankLines="0" />
                                   Indicates that the flow was circuit-broken previously, and is currently
                                   joined upstream to refresh the most recent Bandwidth Advertisement
                                   in order to evaluate reinstating the flow.
                               </t>
                           </list>
                       </t>
                       <t hangText="probe timer">
                           Used to periodically probe a flow in the 'pruned' state, to evaluate
                           returning to 'forwarding'.
                       </t>
                   </list>
               </t>
               <t>
                   Flows additionally have a per-interface state for egress interfaces:
                   <list style="hanging" hangIndent="4">
                       <t hangText="egress status">
                           One of the following values:<list style="empty">
                               <t>* 'forwarding'<vspace blankLines="0" />
                                   Indicates that the flow is a non-circuit-broken flow
                                   in steady state, forwarding data and control packets downstream.
                               </t>
                               <t>* 'blocked'<vspace blankLines="0" />
                                   Indicates that data packets for this flow are NOT forwarded downstream via
                                   this interface. Bandwidth Advertisements are still forwarded, each with the
                                   'Blocked' bit set to 1. All other flow traffic MUST be dropped.
                               </t>
                           </list>
                       </t>
                   </list>
               </t>
           </section>
       </section>
       <section title="Functionality">
           <!-- Required by https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.1.8
                Functionality contained within the building block
                External interfaces.
           -->
               <t>
                   The CBACC building block on a sender MUST have access to the maximum bandwidth
                   that may be sent at any time in the following 3 seconds. A CBACC sender MUST
                   send this value in a Bandwidth Advertisement packet once per second. The end result of
                   the traffic sent on the wire for a particular flow MUST honor this maximum bandwidth
                   commitment, such that bandwidth measurements taken over any one-second period MUST
                   NOT exceed any of prior 3 maximum Bandwidth Advertisements (or any of them, if
                   fewer than 3 have been sent).
               </t>
               <t>
                   A CBACC circuit breaker MUST order its monitored flows based on per-flow estimates of
                   network fairness and preferentially circuit break less fair flows when bandwidth
                   limits are exceeded. A normative method to determine network fairness for a flow is out of
                   scope for this document, but CBACC circuit breaker implementations SHOULD
                   provide a capability for network operators to configure administrative biases
                   for specific sets of flows, and network operators SHOULD consider fairness
                   concerns as expressed in <xref target="RFC2914" /> section 3.2 and other
                   relevant documents containing best practices.
               </t>
               <t>
                   In particular, fairness metrics SHOULD favor multicast flows with
                   many receivers over multicast flows with few receivers and flows with low
                   bandwidth over flows with high bandwidth. When receiver counts are known
                   (for example via the experimental PIM extension specified in <xref target="RFC6807" />)
                   a RECOMMENDED metric is (bandwidth/receiver count), though other metrics MAY
                   be used where deemed appropriate by network operators following internet best practices,
                   or when receiver counts can't be determined.
               </t>
               <t>
                   Bandwidth Advertisement packets MUST NOT be sent by a sender more often than once per
                   second.
               </t>
               <t>
                   If a circuit breaker receives more than 5 Bandwidth Advertisement packets for a
                   flow in two seconds, the circuit breaker SHOULD set the flow to "pruned" and
                   leave the upstream channel, and MUST drop Bandwidth Advertisement packets in
                   excess of one per second.
               </t>
               <t>
                   Flows which are currently circuit-broken on an egress interface are set to
                   "blocked". When an flow on an egress interface is in blocked state, Bandwidth Advertisement
                   packets MUST be forwarded except as described in the preceding paragraph,
                   the "Blocked" bit MUST be set to 1 before forwarding, and other traffic for
                   that flow MUST NOT be forwarded along that interface.
               </t>
               <t>
                   When a flow is blocked or pruned, the circuit breaker MAY truncate the
                   Bandwidth Advertisement packet, keeping only the headers of the packet containing the Bandwidth
                   Advertisement before forwarding.
               </t>
               <t>
                   When a flow is pruned, the circuit-breaker MUST generate and forward a
                   Bandwidth Advertisement packet once per second with the "Blocked" bit set when
                   there are still downstream receivers connected.
               </t>
               <t>
                   In flows which are not circuit-broken but which would be circuit-broken if the
                   bandwidth warning threshold were the bandwidth limit, the Danger bit MUST be
                   set to 1 before forwarding. Both data and control packets are forwarded for flows
                   in this situation. The "Danger" bit MAY be used by receivers to take early action
                   to avoid getting circuit-broken by shifting to a lower-bandwidth representation,
                   if available.
               </t>
               <t>
                   When a flow is in the "blocked" state on every egress interface, the circuit breaker
                   MAY set the flow to "pruned" on the ingress interface and leave the channel upstream.
               </t>
               <t>
                   In addition to monitoring the advertised bandwidth, a CBACC circuit breaker or
                   other assisting nodes in the network SHOULD monitor the observed bandwidth
                   per flow, and SHOULD circuit break "overactive" flows, defined as those which
                   exceed their CBACC maximum bandwidth commitment. A circuit breaker MAY perform constant monitoring
                   on all flows, or MAY use load sharing techniques such as random selection or
                   round robin to monitor only a certain subset of flows at a time. 
               </t>
               <t>
                   When detecting overactive flows, circuit breakers MUST use techniques to avoid
                   false positives due to transient upstream network conditions such as packet
                   compression or occasional packet duplication. For example, using an average of
                   bandwidth measurements over the prior 3 seconds would qualify, where a half-second
                   window would not. (A full listing of reasonable false-positive avoidance techniques
                   is out of scope for this document.)
               </t>
               <t>
                   [TBD: examples with network diagrams and bandwidths?]
               </t>
       </section>
   </section>
   <section title="Requirements from other building blocks">
       <!-- Required by https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.1.8
            Mandatory needs from other building blocks
       -->
       <t>
           The sender needs to know the bandwidth, including any upcoming changes, at least 3 seconds in advance.
           There is no requirement on how building blocks define this functionality except on the packets on the
           wire--the advance knowledge might, for example, be implemented by buffering and pacing on the sending
           machine. Specifics of the sending bandwidth implementations are out of scope for this document, as
           it's intended to provide requirements that will be applicable to a broad range of possible implementations,
           including RTP and WEBRC.
       </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
       <!-- section required by RFC5226 -->
       <t>
           This draft requests IANA to allocate an IPv6 packet header option number
           with the "action" bits set to "skip" and the "change" bit set to 1, as specified in
           <xref target="RFC2460" /> section 4.2.
           [TO BE REMOVED: This registration should take place at the following location:
           http://www.iana.org/assignments/ipv6-parameters/ipv6-parameters.xhtml#extension-header.]
       </t>
       <t>
           This draft also requests IANA to allocate an IPv4 packet header option number with
           the "copied" bit set and the option class "control", as specified in
           <xref target="RFC0791" /> section 3.1.
           [TO BE REMOVED: This registration should take place at the following location:
           http://www.iana.org/assignments/ip-parameters/ip-parameters.xhtml#ip-parameters-1.]
       </t>
       <t>
           If those are deemed unacceptable, as an alternative with some compromises described in
           <xref target="BandwidthAdv" />, this draft instead requests IANA to allocate a UDP destination port
           number.
           [TO BE REMOVED: This registration should take place at the following location:
           http://www.iana.org/assignments/service-names-port-numbers/service-names-port-numbers.xhtml.]
       </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
       <!-- section required by RFC 3552 -->
       <section anchor="sec_forgery" title="Forged Packets">
           <t>
               Forged Bandwidth Advertisement packets that get accepted by CBACC circuit breakers
               which dramatically over-report or under-report the correct bandwidth would present
               a potential DoS against a CBACC flow, by making the circuit breaker believe the
               flow exceeds the node's capacity when over-reporting, or by letting the node notice
               an apparent violation of the commitment to remain under the advertised bandwidth when
               under-reporting.
           </t>
           <t>
               Similarly, it is possible to forge a CBACC Bandwidth Advertisement for a non-CBACC flow,
               which likewise may constitute a DoS against that flow.
           </t>
           <t>
               For multicast, attacker would have to be on-path in order to deliver a forged
               packet to a CBACC circuit breaker, because the join's reverse path propagation
               will only reach the sender on a legitimate network path to its source address.
           </t>
           <t>
               For unicast, it's a bigger problem, because ANY sender along path that doesn't have
               RPF check BCP 38 <xref target="RFC2827" /> permits attack on the flow via forged packet
               that substantially under-reports or over-reports bandwidth.
           </t>
           <t>
               For AMT tunnels, when RPF checks along a path to the gateway are not present,
               nothing stops forged packets from being forwarded by the gateway. If these
               packets contain CBACC control packets, it's possible to inject a forged packet into
               the network downstream from the gateway, combining the unicast hole with the multicast
               hole. This is a vulnerability that should probably be addressed by a new AMT version with
               some defense against forgery of data.
           </t>
           <t>
               For IPSEC, since the Bandwidth Advertisement IP header option is mutable, it's not protected
               by the IPSEC security services, so the Bandwidth Advertisement can be forged for 
               consumption by the circuit breakers, even though the packet will be rejected by the
               end host with the security association. This could mount a DoS via the intermediate
               circuit-breakers by over-reporting or under-reporting flow bandwidth, when processing
               CBACC traffic through untrusted network paths.
           </t>
           <t>
               The unicast vulnerabilities would be much mitigated by RPF checks as recommended
               by BCP 38 <xref target="RFC2827" /> at every hop, or otherwise maintained by
               the network. Absent such checks, cheap DoS vulnerabilities may be present from any
               permissive network locations.
           </t>
       </section>
       <section anchor="sec_slowpath" title="Overloading of Slow Paths">
           <t>
               CBACC control packets are sent as part of the data stream so that they
               traverse the same intermediate network nodes as the rest of the data,
               but they also carry control information that must be processed by certain
               nodes along that path.
           </t>
           <t>
               This creates potential problems very similar to the problems with the Router Alert
               IP option discussed in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC6398" />, where
               a circuit-breaker might have a "fast path" for forwarding that can handle a
               much higher traffic volume than the "slow path" necessary to process CBACC
               control packets, which is potentially vulnerable to overloading.
           </t>
           <t>
               If a CBACC-compatible circuit breaker receives a high rate of CBACC control
               packets, the circuit breaker MUST maintain network health for other flows.
               A circuit-breaker MAY drop all packets, including all CBACC
               control packets, for a flow in which more than 5 CBACC control packets
               were received in less than a second. (This number is intended to allow
               for moderate IP packet duplication and packet compression by upstream
               routers, while still being slow enough for handling of packets on the slow path.)
           </t>
       </section>
       <section anchor="sec_stateexplosion" title="Overloading of State">
           <t>
               Since CBACC flows require state, it may be possible for a set of receivers
               and/or senders, possibly acting in concert, to generate many flows in an
               attempt to overflow the circuit breakers' state tables.
           </t>
           <t>
               It is permissible for a network node to behave as a CBACC circuit breaker
               for some CBACC flows while treating other CBACC flows as non-CBACC, as part
               of a load balancing strategy for the network as a whole, or simply as defense
               against this concern when the number of monitored flows exceeds some threshold.
           </t>
           <t>
               The same techniques described in section 3.1 of <xref target="RFC4609" /> can be used
               to help mitigate this attack, for much the same reasons. It is RECOMMENDED that
               network operators implement measures to mitigate such attacks.
           </t>
       </section>
   </section>

   <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

   <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
       <t>
           Many thanks to Devin Anderson for a detailed review and many great suggestions. Thanks
           also to Cheng Jin and Scott Brown for early feedback.
       </t>
   </section>

 </middle>

 <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     &RFC0791;

     &RFC2113;

     &RFC2119;

     &RFC2460;

     &RFC2711;

     &RFC3048;

     &RFC3738;

     &RFC4302;

     &RFC4727;

     &RFC7761;

     &IEEE.754.1985;

   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     &I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis;

     &I-D.ietf-tsvwg-circuit-breaker;

     &RFC2357;

     &RFC2784;

     &RFC2827;

     &RFC2914;

     &RFC3269;

     &RFC3550;

     &RFC3552;

     &RFC3630;

     &RFC4609;

     &RFC5226;

     &RFC6398;

     &RFC6807;

     &RFC7450;

     <reference anchor="PLM">
         <front>
             <title>Fast Convergence for Cumulative Layered Multicast Transmission Schemes</title>
             <author>
                 <organization>A.Legout, E.W.Biersack, Institut EURECOM</organization>
             </author>
             <date year="1999" />
             <note title="uri"><t>http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.46.8361&amp;rep=rep1&amp;type=pdf"</t></note>
         </front>
     </reference>

   </references>

   <section anchor="overjoining" title="Overjoining">
       <t>
           <xref target="I-D.ietf-tsvwg-rfc5405bis" /> describes several remedies for unicast
           congestion control under UDP, even though UDP does not itself provide congestion control. In
           general, any network node under congestion could in theory collect evidence that a unicast
           flow's sending rate is not responding to congestion, and would then be justified in
           circuit-breaking it.
       </t>
       <t>
           With multicast IP, the situation is different, especially in the presence of malicious receivers.
           A well-behaved sender using a receiver-controlled congestion scheme such as
           WEBRC does not reduce its send rate in response to congestion, instead relying on
           receivers to leave the appropriate multicast groups.
       </t>
       <t>
           This leads to a situation where, when a network accepts inter-domain multicast traffic,
           as long as there are senders somewhere in the world with aggregate bandwidth that exceeds a
           network's capacity, receivers in that network can join the flows and overflow the network
           capacity. A receiver controlled by an attacker could do this at the IGMP/MLD level without
           running the application layer protocol that participates in the receiver-controlled congestion
           control.
       </t>
       <t>
           A network might be able to detect and defend against the most naive version of such an
           attack by blocking end users that try to join too many flows at once. However, an attacker
           can achieve the same effect by joining a few high-bandwidth flows, if those exist anywhere,
           and an attacker that controls a few machines in a network can coordinate the receivers so
           they join disjoint sets of non-responsive sending flows.
       </t>
       <t>
           This scenario will produce congestion in a middle node in the network that can't be
           easily detected at the edge where the IGMP/MLD join is accepted. Thus, an attacker with
           a small set of machines in a target network can always trip a circuit breaker if present,
           or can induce excessive congestion among the bandwidth allocated to multicast. This problem
           gets worse as more multicast flows become available.
       </t>
       <t>
           This is a significant barrier to multicast adoption because there is no present defense
           which does not itself constitute a denial of service attack.
       </t>
       <t>
           Although the same can apply to non-responsive unicast traffic, network operators can
           assume that non-responsive sending flows are in violation of congestion control best
           practices, and can therefore cut off such flows. However, non-responsive multicast
           senders are likely to be well-behaved participants in receiver-controlled congestion
           control schemes.
       </t>
       <t>
           However, receiver controlled congestion control schemes also show the most promise
           for efficient massive scale content distribution via multicast, provided 
           network health can be ensured. Therefore, mechanisms to mitigate overjoining attacks while
           still permitting receiver-controlled congestion control are necessary.
       </t>
       <figure align="center" anchor="overjoining_diagram">
           <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
TBD: network diagram
]]></artwork>
       </figure>
   </section>

   <!--
     Requirements on this draft (references below):

     From 1. https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2357#section-5:

   a. Analyze the behavior of the protocol.
      The vulnerabilities and performance problems must be shown through
      analysis. Especially the protocol behavior must be explained in
      detail with respect to scalability, congestion control, error
      recovery, and robustness.

      For example the following questions should be answered:

         How scalable is the protocol to the number of senders or
         receivers in a group, the number of groups, and wide dispersion
         of group members?

         Identify the mechanisms which limit scalability and estimate
         those limits.

         How does the protocol protect the Internet from congestion? How
         well does it perform? When does it fail?

         Under what circumstances will the protocol fail to perform the
         functions needed by the applications it serves?
         Is there a congestion control mechanism? How well does it
         perform? When does it fail?  Note that congestion control
         mechanisms that operate on the network more aggressively than
         TCP will face a great burden of proof that they don't threaten
         network stability.

   b. Include a description of trials and/or simulations which support
      the development of the protocol and the answers to the above
      questions.

   c. Include an analysis of whether the protocol has congestion
      avoidance mechanisms strong enough to cope with deployment in the
      Global Internet, and if not, clearly document the circumstances in
      which congestion harm can occur.  How are these circumstances to
      be prevented?

   d. Include a description of any mechanisms which contain the traffic
      within limited network environments. If the analysis in a or c
      shows that the protocol has potential to damage the Internet, then
      the analysis must include a discussion of ways to limit the scope
      or otherwise contain the protocol.  We recognize that the
      confinement of Internet applications is an open research area.

   e. Reliable multicast protocols must include an analysis of how they
      address a number of security and privacy concerns.  If the
      protocol can be used in different modes of secure operation, then
      each mode must be analyzed.

         The analysis must document which of the various parties -
         senders, routers (more generally, data forwarders), receivers,
         retransmission sources - must be trusted in order to ensure
         secure operation and privacy of the transmitted data, to what
         degree, and why.  (One issue to address here are "man-in-the-
         middle" attacks.)

         To what degree can data be manipulated so that at least a
         subset of the receivers receive different copies?  Does the
         protocol allow a group of receivers to determine whether they
         all received the same data?

         What limitations are placed on the retransmission mechanism to
         prevent it from being abused to flood network links with
         excessive traffic? Which parties must be trusted to ensure
         this, and to what degree, and why? The presumption will be that
         either a congestion control mechanism will inherently limit the
         volume of retransmission traffic, and that this limiting

         influence is robust under concerted attack; or that
         retransmission requests will be signed in a cryptographically
         strong manner so that abuses of the mechanism can be traced
         back to their source.  Protocols that do not provide either of
         these forms of protection face a great burden of proof that
         they don't threaten network stability.

         What sort of key management does the protocol require, and
         provide for?



     From 2. https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.1.8:

   Rationale
      _  Provide justification for the building block's existence
      _  Provide rationale for the building block's granularity

   Functionality
      _  Functionality contained within the building block
      _  External interfaces

   Applicability Statement
      _  Intended usage
      _  Failure modes (including means of detection if known)
      _  Environmental considerations
      _  Incompatibilities / Conflicts with other building blocks

   Packet Header Fields
      _  Specification of logical packet-header fields (*)
      _  Abstract messages specifications (*)

   Requirements from other building blocks;
      _  Mandatory needs from other building blocks

   Security Considerations
      _  Specify as much as possible (with respect to procedures,
         algorithms and data encoding), without affecting the general
         applicability of the building block.




     Documents especially pertinent to requirements on this draft:

     1. Technical criteria for Reliable Multicast:
        https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2357#section-5

     2. Author Guidelines for Reliable Multicast Transport Building Blocks
        https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3269#section-2.1.8

   -->
   <!-- Change Log

v00 2016-10-03  JEH   Initial version
   -->
 </back>
</rfc>
